A Guide to the Records of Radford College, the Women's Division of Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1953-1959
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of Radford College, the Women's Division of Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1953-1959
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 24
0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box
This collection consists of reports by the Radford College faculty for the Intervisitation Committee of the American Association of Colleges of Teacher Education, 1953; blank forms, instructions, and form letters by M'Ledge Moffett, 1953; undated items about the honor system; and a 1959 report to the Board of Visitors.
Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Radford College
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Records of Radford College, the Women's Division of Virginia Polytechnic Institute were transferred to Special Collections prior to 1978.
Administrative History
Established in 1910, the State Normal and Industrial School for Women at Radford was renamed the State Teachers College at Radford in 1924. The college merged with Virginia Tech on June 23, 1944, to become Radford College, the Women's Division of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute. VPI's president became chancellor and chief administrator of Radford College. In 1963, the Board of Visitors made an official request to the Governor to dissolve the VPI- Radford College merger. The separation became effective July 1, 1964. In 1979, the Radford College became Radford University.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of the 1953 reports relative to the standards of the American Association of Colleges of Teacher Education, prepared by the Radford College faculty for the Intervisitation Committee of the Association. The collection also contains personnel records with blank forms, instructions, and form letters by M'Ledge Moffett, Dean of Women, 1953; undated items about the honor system; and a 1959 report to the Board of Visitors.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Items concerning the Radford-VPI merger, 1943-44, can be found in the Records of the Office of the President, Julian A. Burruss (RG 2/8), and additional Radford College reports can be found in the Records of the Virginia Tech Board of Visitors (RG 1).
Index Terms
Subjects:
University Archives; University History; Women -- History
Organizations:
Radford College; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Personnel Records, 1953-03-1953-08 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Report to the Board of Visitors for the Quarter ending December 31, 1959, 1960-02-01 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Honor System Rules and Procedures, nd (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reports of the Intervisitation Committee of American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1953:
  - Procedures Followed by Radford Faculty for Preparation for Intervisitation Committee of AACTE, Committee Summaries and Recommendations by Standards, Faculty Evaluation Graph, Student Evaluation, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Standard I - Definition, Objectives, and Organization of a College for Teacher Education, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Standard II - Student Personnel Services, [1953] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Standard III - Preparation of Faculty, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Standard V - Curriculum Instructional Patterns, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Standard V - Advanced Professional Programs, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Standard VI - Secondary Education, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Standard VI - Professional Laboratory Experiences, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Standard VII - The Library, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)